- That is a lot to comprehend isn't it?
- May I ask, seeing as
we can do all of this,
would we be able to
change their eye colour?
- Makes sense that someone would go there.
- Well it's just that my granddad
had green eyes and none
of our kids have it.
Be really nice to carry that on, you know?
- They're polygenic traits.
So they're more complicated
than you'd imagine.
- But you could attempt to change a number
of attributes like hair colour and height.
If you really wanted to.
- Are we sure this is wise
power to give parents?
Look at the stupid names
people give to their kids.
- Yeah, I mean when I was
pregnant I couldn't even
decide what socks to
put on in the morning.
So I'd hate to think what
choices I would've made.
- I don't see this sort of editing
being something many people would want.
- You've heard of cosmetic surgery, right?
- Yes, but what -
- That's not short of takers is it?
And just think, that
went from reconstructive
plastic surgery to pec,
breast and butt implants
or whatever it is that's fashionable now.
- I can't see anything wrong with that.
- How about the effects of
a fashion for lighter skin?
Or slender bodies or western eyes?
- That's not a thing.
- I think you'll find it is.
And isn't it a bit weird the parents
choosing how the child looks?
- So we can change their eye colour?
- If I were you, I'd
concentrate on changing
their intelligence more
than their eye colour.
- What are you trying to say?
- I'm just saying that if we're
to use this technology properly
then we should concentrate more
on those things that
create the greatest impact.
Like intelligence, athletic
ability if you will.
- Isn't that going a bit too far though?
- And changing their eye colour isn't?
- No, it's...
No, it's just...
- Well imagine I edit my
children to become the smartest
most intelligent that
technology could allow.
Where might this leave your children?
- I'd make my kids the the
smartest they could be.
- Intelligence isn't just
one particular thing.
You do know that, right?
- Yes, of course.
But if I give to my children the relevant
genetic talents to make
the most of this world,
then they will have had
the basis of all the things
they need to achieve
success and happiness.
- You say that as if environment
has nothing to do with it.
- Of course it does.
But what if they do it, and them,
and both your neighbours
and your best friend?
Imagine how it'd feel to
have your child fall behind
because you choose not to
help them and others did.
- I take back what I
said about eye colour.
It's just sometimes you
can go a bit too far.
- It would be about money anyway.
- But that's wrong, isn't it?
- Once a technology exists,
there's no stopping it.
You just have to embrace it.
- But why can't you stop it?
- Because it would never work.
- Why?
- Because it wouldn't.
- Would you really like to see
edits of this nature stopped?
- Yeah, yeah, I think I would.
I just think that there's got to be
a line that we shouldn't cross.
Right?
- What about you?
I mean this is interesting.
Because we aren't talking
about a change to stop
something potentially
restricting their life.
We're talking about an enhancement
beyond what it was destined to be.
And enhancements like
this are complex, right?
Your view of aesthetics or intelligence.
Is maybe different to what it is to me.
A lesson too.
I may value speed, you endurance.
But there is a causality to the answers.
For if your child is edited,
and the rest of us choose not to.
Then.
- But in the end don't we
all just want the same thing?
To make our children's
lives the best they can be?
And if we can achieve that
through this technology
then why wouldn't we want to do it?
- I see that...
I think there's a real possibility
for this technology to do some good.
It could make people's lives better.
But I think a lot of things.
Could have made my son's life better.
And none of them are answered
in the question of changing who he was.
- None?
- None.
- Well I'm definitely
gonna be enhancing my kids.
- And I guess there lies our problem.
- Would you enhance your child?