- But what's that gonna mean?
- If you let yourself,
you can really imagine what the decisions
you made could mean.
The path you've lit forward.
I think that in knowing in the early days,
they will rely on us for everything,
it can drive a fear that
can drive you to want
to protect them from whatever you can.
But when I cast my mind
into the future of this
life I have created,
all I hope is that it is
a life lived joyously,
freely, fulfilled.
I think if I had a wish for them,
it would be that it
would have the security
to be who they wanted to be,
to find a purpose that brings
them more happiness than pain.
Because, well,
because isn't that the best
we can hope for in life?
And I can't see why that's
not achievable for most,
if not all children.
And I suspect that it's less
about choosing the children
that come into the world
than choosing a better
world for these children
to come into.
For our problem is and always has been
how we ensure that
better world comes about.