- Welcome.
And thank you for joining us today.
Choosing Children is a live,
interactive experience.
Your role will be passive,
not insignificant, but passive.
So please remain silent throughout.
Do not get up from your
chair until the end,
unless you need to leave the experience.
And please ensure all
mobiles are switched off.
Through the experience,
you will be asked a series of questions,
which I will repeat to you.
Answer these by clicking on
the device in front of you.
The questions will be testing,
and if you do not feel capable
of attempting to answer them,
or if it becomes too much,
you are absolutely free to leave
the way you came in.
But remember, you would not be here
if you could not help.
This is a safe space
for us to unravel the difficult questions
you are to hear together.
We are in uncharted territory,
and as yet there is no right or wrong.
Not yet.
No one will know the answers you give,
but your answer will be linked
to what happens in the space.
So consider them and answer
as honestly as you can.
Now, check those phones
are off one more time
and say those words that
cannot wait until after
to those that you came with.
Ready?
Okay.
Let's begin.