- We have a problem.
You see, in this time
before memory existed,
out of nothing...
a universe was created so big, so massive,
it is impossible to comprehend
in any meaningful way.
But in one small corner of
that vast, vast universe,
through pure chance and the
great infiniteness of time,
a proliferation of life emerged,
life that would eventually become us.
If you think about it,
from the birth of that first star
when everything that has ever existed
or will ever exist emerged, to now,
the probability of us
existing at all is unlikely.
Ridiculous, even.
But here we are.
Me and you.
And, that makes us all pretty special
in our own unique way.
For most of our existence,
even if we knew very well the act
that led to the development of life,
we knew little detail of
exactly how we were created.
Yet a mother
could still feel the
flutter of new life inside,
the changes in ones body,
the growing bump to know
that the potential of
life existed within them.
And, when this bump grew enough,
new life is born.
Life fraught with the
responsibility of its dependency,
of untold challenges, and reward.
And, oh, how much reward it can bring.
Indescribable joy and an
unspeakable bond that...
that... is almost beyond
our simple understanding.
For some, it can be one of
the greatest achievements
we can ever make.
But from the darkness of this unknown
both natural curiosity and a
burning desire for knowledge
led us to light..
In the blink of an eye
we leapt from measuring the size of a bump
to looking within it.
Scans revealed life as it exists here,
the cord, the sac, a tiny waving hand,
the beating of their heart.
We recorded information on each
and every little growing life we could.
And then we learnt to do more than look.
We discovered the code of life itself.
DNA, Deoxyribonucleic acid, they call it.
It's not important to
know exactly what it is,
or to worry about the
coding, non-coding dilemma.
All you need to know is, it is the code,
born of when your father's
sperm met your mother's egg,
that instructed every gene, every cell,
tissue, skin cell,
every ounce of blood,
every organ to be created,
so you could become you.
Over time, we researched and
explored what DNA could do,
finally laying out the human genome,
the entire set of
instructions of our being,
a genetic map of ourselves.
Through this prism, the
very knowledge of genetics
began to shape how we think and understand
all living beings.
In no time at all, a sample of your hair,
or a swab of your mouth
could reveal your history,
understand your present,
and predict your future.
We know genetics is not
all there is, far from it,
but they are the core,
the building blocks,
the foundation of life that
shape and evolve with us.
Soon enough we learnt to
shape those very foundations,
to control what once we could not.
And, these new abilities
in genetic engineering,
makes every action, every inaction
in the genetic development
of our children a choice.
A power both awesome and terrifying,
the moral dilemmas that
arise from this power
may be the biggest
humanity has ever faced.
That is why today
I need to know what role
genetic engineering will play
in the development of our unborn children.
For when the fate of humanity is at sake..
There can be greater
responsibility, no greater urgency,
to the answers we seek.
For us to find the true
answers to these dilemmas,
I need to ask you to place yourself
in the role of an expectant parent.
Think of this as a test
of your imagination,
a role play, if you like.
So, lets go on this journey together.
Close your eyes if you will
and lets imagine what it is
to be this expectant parent.
Imagine that first
pregnancy test turning blue,
or the confirmation of successful IVF,
the ecstasy of knowing,
and the trepidation of
having created a new life,
and the practicality of what that life
may mean to your every day.
Imagine yourself in the heyday
of your life or maybe not;
prepared most likely not,
because we never are
but still in a position
to bring new life into this world.
If you really cannot get there,
maybe take the role of a supportive friend
or family member...
Are we there?
Okay, hold that thought in your mind
and open your eyes, if you will.
Don't lose that thought.
Keep holding.
Here are your fragile new lives.
Each one an individual,
linked to the decisions you,
and you alone make.
Each one a child to be, a
child cherished and wanted.
Yearned and planned for.
A parent to them you wish...
wish desperately to be.
And, I want to ask if for
this fragile little life,
we are imagining bringing into the world
if would you consider changing it?
Changing the genetic makeup
that it was originally destined to have?
For in a time before now,
our ignorance, our inability,
protected us from the questions
of altering our own species...
But not now and not for you
because it is these questions,
of altering our own species
that I'm am seeking
answers for from you...
So, I wonder, from the
little I have explained
and what you already know,
could you ever imagine
using genetic engineering
to change your unborn child?