- I don't know if I expected more of you
would have consider using this technology
to genetically alter your child.
- Changing the genetic destiny
of living beings is nothing new,
because even before we
knew the world to be round,
humanity has known
something of the cultivation
of life's genetic codes.
Through our interventions,
we turned small wild horses
into huge, strong thoroughbreds,
wolves into Great Danes and sausage dogs,
and domesticated most of the cereals
and plant-based foods that
adorn people's plates today.
For millennia, a system of
trial and error was our only way
to shape life to fit our purpose.
But with our new genetic
engineering technology,
we can pinpoint the smallest
of genetic changes we want to make
and change the course
of life's development.
- Giving us the power
to not only create life
but to control it,
making us the gods of
ours, and others, destiny.
- Yes, in a way.
Using these technologies
and the maps of life we have created,
we have genetically engineered
drought-resistant plants,
fluorescent mice, and
self-destructive mosquitoes.
And, when it comes to us,
it has pushed our ability
to change the next generations of humanity
in ways we could almost of never imagined.
- And that always starts
with genetic screening?
- Yes, in order to enact any alterations,
the unborn child would need
to undergo genetic screening.
These tell us more than the sex
and apparent visual health of a child,
they can tell us intimate
details about their health,
development potential, and life chances.
- And some might say it reveals too much.
- Do they?
- Would you want somebody
to know all about you,
your history, your potential?
- This is not about me.
- Because these scans lay bare everything
that was once a journey
of discovery and surprise.
We'd be told the likely colour
of their hair, their eyes,
the shape of their ears,
even the likely amount
of sleep they'll need.
- Just because we perform such a scan,
it does not mean the parents
would have to use all
the information we have.
- That may be, but we'd know it,
and we have to acknowledge
there's always an inherent danger
in where knowledge like that can take us.
- Well, think of the
advantages of scans like these.
Most of the time,
they will reveal nothing
of major importance,
but think of all those diseases
that can hide within our genes
that we could catch and
prevent at an early stage.
- If only it would be that simple.
Because often we aren't
talking about absolutes,
we're talking about percentages,
a statistic on the chance
of something happening,
and we'd be basing all future
decisions on that percentage.
- In some ways,
I struggle to imagine
what this child would be.
In others, I see them as clear as day.
I know what I receive on a
bit of paper will not be then,
but I cannot help but wonder
what effects knowing
more about them may do
to how I treat them,
how I see them.
- At this stage, it is just a scan.
What would you have to
lose from taking it?
- This is almost a redundant question
for those of you that have already said
you would consider genetically
engineering your child,
as this is a precursor for that.
But, but let us start afresh.
Would you like to know
as much as you could
about your unborn child by
using genetic screening,
or would you still like
that natural mysticism?