- In this form,
I know it's not a child yet,
in the sense it does not
smile at the sight of a parent
or a little wind.
It cannot wrap its whole hand
around one's little finger,
and it cannot stare into its eyes and see.
But it has all the potential
to be smaller than a millimetre.
Yet it has all the
instructions it needs to grow
and become the life we desire.
This does not.
No, you do not need to say.
This knowledge has come
about because of this scan?
- It has.
- Could we have found this another way?
- Possibly.
But there would likely be
no hope in that knowledge,
only pain.
- For all this knowledge,
it's still a fact
that not all pregnancies go
the way one expects or wants.
And how unbelievable joy can
turn to unbelievable sadness,
for it has always been the case
that some life will shine and fade
without anyone knowing they ever existed.
Some life will fade out of choice,
others against the will
of expecting parents,
nearly always without fault or blame.
It's as painful an experience
as one could imagine at life
not lived ended far too soon.
A pain many of us have shared.
A pain there's been very
little we could do to prevent
and know what we might do to change that.
- I know the pain you talk of.
And coming through it,
I know that was a path I
and they had to travel.
- Given the choice,
would you have wanted to
try and save their life?
- I think at the time,
I would've done anything
to hold him in my arms.
But,
I've come to terms with the fact
that it was a life that
was not meant to be.
However much I wanted it to live,
its path was not that.
And with time,
I've learned to accept the fact
that that's just a part of life.
- But with genetic engineering,
there may have been
something we could have done.
- But still.
I'm not sure I could have gone that far.
- Think of it like life-saving surgery.
You would not deny a
child that, would you?
- But I don't think those
two things are the same.
- No, not exactly, but
both are interventions.
Say instead of a metal scalpel
and a special patch to
repair a hole in one's heart,
coded RNA seeks and replaces
errors in our genetic code
to intervene before a
hole could even form.
It cannot save every life,
but for those that it can...
- It's not as if you're
correcting something
that you hold in your hands.
You're changing what that
child was meant to be,
and altering that feels like...
- Like we are altering their destiny.
- Like all interventions do.
Remember, we are simply
tweaking their code
to ensure they have a chance of life.
We are changing nothing
that can't already exist.
- I don't believe that to be true.
I think instinctively,
you might want to do everything you could,
but it might not be one simple
intervention that does it.
You might end up changing
the child in so many ways.
It brings into question at what point
it's still the child you conceived.
- What wrong could be done to a life
if its alternative is no life at all?
- It's not that.
It's not a straightforward a question
as you make it out to be.
And I just wonder.
Is that a fair ask
of a parent for a child
that was not destined to be?
- When it might be the
only thing we could do
to save their life,
I don't think we have
a choice except to ask.
- Nothing would stop
me from saying, "Yes."
- Could there be
a more delicate question than this?
Although we refer to
this as an unborn child,
it is both a child, not a child,
and an intervention in
such a natural process,
however painful, is...
Please if you can, I'd like to know
if you would be willing
to use genetic engineering
to attempt to save your unborn child
if it was the only option.
Even if that meant
changing the very nature
of what that child was meant to be.