- Will this one survive?
- It's probably too early to tell.
- But there is hope.
- There's always hope.
- This technology has the potential
to bring hope to millions.
With its power, we can make interventions
in ways we previously only dreamt of.
Because the process of screening
and editing our children
not only allows us to hunt down reasons
that cause a life to end too soon,
it can help us to find and
prevent the genetic diseases
and abnormalities that will
affect their later life.
For example, there is a particular gene
that if it is carried by the
parent and passed to the child,
that child will have an
extraordinarily high chance
of developing breast cancer.
- Very few of us carry those genes
- Still.
Could you imagine just for a minute,
sitting with your child,
suffering through
procedure after procedure
with a disease caused
by the genetic material you gave to them
that you choose to do nothing about?
- I would assume, in most of these cases,
an intervention could be made
later in their development.
- What do you mean by that?
- Well, if I'm right,
in this example,
we are talking about
altered versions of BRCA1,
although it could be various others.
Variants of these genes
can increase the risk
of getting breast cancer,
but there are options one can
take once a child is born.
- That may be, but why take the risk?
Surely, it's better to
ensure they cannot happen
in the first place.
- Well, from a medical perspective,
I can certainly see the benefits
of using genetic editing
to eliminate serious congenital diseases
or high-risk mutations before
a foetus reaches full term.
But, these conditions that
we talk of can vary hugely
in terms of the effects
on a person's life,
their presentation, and
severity of symptoms.
If we cannot accurately predict the impact
of eliminating or changing one's genes,
then we could not
ethically make the decision
to make those alterations.
- I think we are overcomplicating this.
Remember, an intervention of this nature
stops the potential of
something cruel and painful
before it even has the
chance to manifest itself.
It will not stop all cancers,
but imagine for those
parents that carry risk
how freeing it could be to remove it.
- But as I said before, at this stage,
parents would be calculating risk
and making decisions
on a percentage chance
of something possibly
happening way in the future.
Decisions a child would not have a say in.
- In these cases,
percentage or no percentage,
surely the impact of our
inaction will have more risk
than any action we could take.
- No one can dispute cancer is.
And passing a gene hidden
in our own genetic code
that poses them risk is.
It feels natural to try and protect one
from such illnesses we could pass on them.
But to talk about making a change now
to potentially save their life
in five, 10, 50, 80
years from now is just...
- I'd say it comes down to
if you feel you should
make these decisions
not fully knowing what
the consequences would be,
or you wait
to make an intervention.
- When it could be too late.
When it could be too late.
- When the level of risk
could be better understood.
- Would you want to remove genes
from your child that might
pose them a risk in the future,
or would you prefer to give them some role
in this decision later in life
if that was possible?