- This doesn't have to stop there.
Bestowed upon us is a great opportunity
to ensure no child suffers as a result
of their genetic makeup.
We could intervene to
ensure no child is born
with congenital blindness, deafness.
- Hold on.
A lot of deaf people
wouldn't consider their
impairment a disadvantage.
- Culturally, maybe not.
But if we can make alterations
before a child is born,
why impair them at all?
- I suppose you're applying
this to Down syndrome, autism,
people who are small in stature, right?
- If it could give them a better life.
- The thing is, there's
no real way to ensure
any of the changes we make
will make their life better.
The only way to ensure
that is through the actions
we take in life.
- To believe that would be to believe
there is no innate benefit
to being able to hear, see, or walk.
- But those traits are only
beneficial in a society
which refuses to accommodate difference.
- I'm not denying that.
What I'm saying is that
why make it an issue
in the first place?
Isn't it better to remove all traits
that might prevent a
child having a great life?
Would that not be a key to
a fairer, happier society
than the one we have now?
- How about better education,
better healthcare provisions,
nurturing environments?
- Yes, I agree, but I'm
also saying that morally
and logically, if we can ensure
that our children can live
unhindered by disability-
- There will still be disabled people.
Unless you think you can
eliminate a genetic predisposition
towards car accidents.
- I'm not denying that
disability will still exist
in some form, but it's not like before,
where if you got a test result
and it presented you
with a child or situation
you didn't think you could handle,
Down syndrome, for example, previously,
more often than not, the
only option was abortion.
But now, we could just change the child.
- I don't even know
how to respond to that.
- If I may?
- Of course, go on.
- As I've been listening,
I've been asking myself
if I had a choice, would
I have chosen my son?
It feels wrong to even
be considering that.
He's my son, after all.
The way I look at it,
ultimately, is like this.
Yes, he could be difficult sometimes.
Yes, it was exhausting,
but he wouldn't have been
him without his traits.
Who he is,
how he thought, what he said.
So yes.
Some days, he drove me nuts
and it felt like I
couldn't stand it anymore,
and that, that was rubbish for us both.
But some days, he could be so
gentle and loving and funny.
And I remembered that really,
everyone is like that.
Everyone has good days and tricky days.
Just because I could have chosen a child
that didn't have those genes,
it doesn't mean that
I would've had a child
that was any,
however much it may have
made my life easier.
So no,
in the end,
I don't think it was or should
have been my responsibility
to change my child.
It was just my job to
love him, and I did that.
But surely, an alteration could
have made their life better?
- You know what?
I don't think it could.
- Life is just too complex for alterations
like this alone to make a parent
or child's life better.
- Really?
Imagine this then.
You've got three kids,
and one of them has special needs,
which means that the other two are always
being put last, you know?
Because of the special one, they'd suffer,
the kids would suffer and
the parents would suffer too.
Who wants that?
No one benefits.
It's just more time, more
money, and more hard work.
Where's the reward?
Look, I'm not being funny,
but some people are
basically just vegetables.
And then they die.
What sort of life is that
to wish for your kids?
It's better not to live
than to live like that.
Well, I know I'd be bloody miserable
if that was my life.
Assuming that is that
I've got the intelligence
to know how shit my life was
and how miserable I am.
It's a quick tweak.
That's all that's needed,
and then you're saved,
claiming benefits for
the rest of your life.
People might not like this
idea, but it's the truth.
- I'm not sure how helpful
phrasing it that way is,
but there is some truth in it.
Our children have always been subject
to the lottery of genetics.
Sometimes, it's good, sometimes bad,
but if we can alter a child's genetic code
before it's born to improve
its chances of a good life,
then surely, in the interest of the child,
we should be obliged to do it.
To refrain from changing
a child's genetics
if we're able to do so,
especially if not to do so
would lead to them suffering
would be wrong.
- I'm not sure.
I've been thinking about
would I choose to be disabled?
I've thought about it a lot, trust me.
Didn't have much else to do some days
than ponder my existence
and how much better off
people would feel without me.
Sorry, bit grim.
But when you spend your whole life,
literally, your whole life being treated
like you're a burden,
are not always outwardly, but sometimes.
Mostly it's subliminal though.
The look of pity in a stranger's eyes.
The never seeing someone like me on TV.
And it's not just that.
It's not just everyone else's bullshit.
It's the reality of it too.
Sometimes,
I'm in pain
and people don't really understand.
They try really hard.
I know they do,
but you can't understand
unless you live it,
unless you're in pain 24/7.
And sometimes even when
I do everything right,
I still have flare ups
and I can't walk at all.
And I feel so shit for needing
everyone to take care of me.
And I can't even
concentrate on feeling shit
because I'm in so much pain.
That's the worst.
But it's not always like that.
And as much as I'd love
to never have another one
of those days, I don't
think I'd rather be dead.
Because that's the thing, isn't it?
It's not like if my
parents had had the scan,
they'd be choosing
between me being disabled
and me not being disabled.
They'd be choosing between
me and no me at all.
Because changing my disability
means I wouldn't be who I am.
- So like you wouldn't hold
against your mom and dad
if they could have made the
decision and just didn't?
- All I can say is
as much as I hate myself some days
for the way that I am,
I am who I am.
I wouldn't wanna be anyone else.
- Would you use genetic engineering
to change your unborn child,
So to remove an impairment,
a disability, if you will,
if one was discovered in your child?