- I can see why that may be.
Would you be happy to explain more
and we can interpret for you?
Sure, I want my child
to come into the world
full of breath, life, a
healthy baby, Deaf or hearing.
But also, it would be funny to say
I hadn't thought about
raising a Deaf child.
I would be lying.
I'm Deaf.
I have a beautiful life.
As a child growing up
in the 80s, it was hard.
My environment was very hearing,
family, school, and I just
didn't know how to be me.
In a world that every
day taught me, told me
because I wasn't hearing
there was a fault with me.
That was wrong.
But eventually I found my tribe, friends,
my culture, the Deaf community.
That's the beauty of my world.
I know that to have and
to raise a Deaf child,
they can have that too.
- Surely we can't allow that.
- Why not?
- Because you'd be making it deaf.
- And? You're missing the point.
A child is a child.
A Deaf child can really soar at life.
- This really is madness.
- You don't understand.
But even that's a bit much.
- I think it goes without saying
that I'm for parental choice,
but it has to be
questioned if it conflicts
with the right of the
child to an open future.
Put simply, what if the child grows up
and no longer wants to be deaf?
- I'll tell you what.
The parent would've messed
the child up. That's what.
- Harmed, I think is the more
appropriate language here.
- Harmed? I would never.
- I'm sure you wouldn't mean to,
but if they grew up not wanting to be deaf
and that was a decision
that you had made for them,
then unfortunately there's
probably no other way
of describing it.
- Your response is typical, expected.
Everything up to this point that I said
about my lived experience,
why I want a Deaf child,
has gone in one ear and out the other.
Perhaps you're just not ready
for this type of conversation.
I understand.
I know that it is not for you,
but would you be happy for
me to describe deafness
as an impairment?
Your words.
Would you consider using this technology
to ensure your child had a trait
that others may consider an
impairment such as deafness?