(soft music)
- I have a problem.
You see,
in a time before memory existed
out of nothing,
(exploding sound)
a universe was created.
So big.
So massive.
It's impossible to comprehend
in any meaningful way.
And in one small corner
of that
vast,
vast universe
through pure chance
and the great infiniteness of time,
a proliferation of life emerged.
Life that would eventually become us.
For most of our existence
we knew little of the details of exactly
how we were created.
Until one day, our knowledge
our technologies allowed us to
discover the building blocks
for life itself.
And in the blink of an eye
we went from mapping our
creation to editing it.
Giving us the power to
not only create life
but to control it.
Making us the gods
of our
and others
destiny
and the moral dilemmas
that arise from this
may be the biggest
humanity has ever faced.
So today
I ask you
what role genetic engineering should play
in the development of our unborn children.
(soft music)